# Simon Holmbacka. PhD – Resume 13 July 2016

Contact Information Embedded Systems Laboratory Faculty of Science and Engineering Åbo Akademi University, Finland

Frantsinkatu 2 B 9 20540 Turku, Finland Tel: +358 50 5310467 Email: sholmbac@abo.fi Gender: male

Time of birth: 24.01.1986

Place of birth: Jakobstad, Finland

Nationality: Finnish

Position

#### Post-Doc Researcher

Åbo Akademi University Finland. Faculty of Science and Engineering,

Embedded Systems Laboratory. Task: Post-doc research and teaching Wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter

Fernuniversität in Hagen, Germany. Lehrgebiet Parallelität & VLSI

Task: Post-doc research and teaching

January 2016 -

September 2015 -

#### EDUCATION

#### Åbo Akademi University, Finland

Doctor of Technology in Computer Engineering (26 Jan. 2016, Turku, Finland)

2011 - 2015

- Faculty: Science and Engineering
- Major: Embedded Computer Systems
- Minor: Software Engineering
- Minor: University Pedagogics
- Thesis: Energy-Aware Software for Many-Core Systems Grade: Honorary Grade
- Reference: Prof. Johan Lilius johan.lilius@abo.fi

Master of Science in Computer Engineering (31 Mar. 2011, Turku, Finland)

2009 - 2011

- Institution: Information Technologies
- Major: Embedded Computer Systems
- Minor: Control Engineering
- Minor: Software Engineering
- Thesis: Task Migration in Virtualized Multi-Core Real-Time Systems Grade: 5/5

Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering (6 Oct. 2009, Turku, Finland)

2006 - 2009

- Institution: Information Technologies
- Major: Embedded Computer Systems
- Minor: Software Engineering

About Me

I come from the small city of Jakobstad in the mid west of Finland from which I moved to Turku to study computer engineering in 2006. I completed my Master's degree in 5 years (2006 - 2011) and my PhD in 4 years (2011 – 2015) from Åbo Akademi University in Turku, Finland.

Technical

I have worked extensively in the areas of embedded systems, runtime systems, power management and manycore platforms, which includes foremost low level system programming (usually in C). Furthermore I have experience in object oriented programming languages, mostly C++ and Java, and I have of course stumbled upon some Python, C#, .net, VB, Java script, xml and assembly programming. I have worked with system modeling, mathematical optimization and control theory including NLP optimization, digital filtering, plane fitting methods, control theory and its underlying mathematics. This means that I have very good knowledge of Matlab, its toolboxes and system simulation in Simulink. On the hardware side, I have excellent knowledge of ARM and Intel platforms in particular, and system/kernel programming using Linux. I have been hacking with the Linux kernel since I was 16 years old and know this world in and out. From my PhD work, I created an Android app called "Low Energy Player" freely available on Google Play. On further lower level I have worked with real-time operating systems like FreeRTOS during my PhD and I have also build many hobby projects from scratch using micro controllers such as an audio synthesizer complete with a midi interface and USB driver running on an 8-bit AVR.

#### Project Work

In the 4 years of making my PhD I have published over 15 international peer reviewed scientific articles, one of which I received the best paper award for in 2014. I worked in the European FP-7 project RECOMP from 2011 - 2014 and in the national Tekes project ParallaX from 2014 - 2016, in which I worked together with universities and international IT companies like Wittenstein ltd., UK and Seven Solutions, Spain on programming and integration tasks. I am a very good team worker, which has shown in co-operations with 7 different universities in 4 countries during this time for my thesis, and outside of my thesis I have published work together with 12 different institutions and co-authored work together with over 30 people. I have visited more than 30 countries in my thesis work, and I find it very easy to join a team and start working on new projects with new people.

#### Languages

#### 

• Swedish: Mother tongue • Finnish: Conversational

• English: Fluent • German: Conversational

#### Pedagogics

Education wise, I have been lecturing university courses in English since 2013 and completed university pedagogics as a minor subject. I created an online education MooC on coursera.org from scratch in the EIT Digital project in 2015 and 2016, which is now freely available on Coursera and has over 4000 active students. https://www.coursera.org/learn/real-time-systems/

### About Simon

I would describe myself as a person who takes the initiative and gets things started. I have a very good working discipline with regard to time and responsibility, and I always do the work today instead of leaving it until tomorrow! I always start a task well on time, and I keep the promised timelines whether it is a question of delivering C code, an article, a presentation, course material or a PhD thesis.

My hobbies – besides embedded systems hacking – are traveling, gardening, skiing, hiking and workout.

#### Teaching Experience

#### Course creator and lecturer: EIT Digital Online Coursera

Development of Real-Time Systems https://www.coursera.org/learn/real-time-systems/	Spring 2016
Advisor and examiner for thesis work: Åbo Akademi University	2012 - 2016

Prufer für Abschlussarbeiten: FernUniversität in Hagen	2015 - 2016
Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2016
Course assistant: Multimedia Algorithm Implementations Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2016
Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2015
Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2014
Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2013
Course assistant: Multimedia Algorithm Implementations Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2013
Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2012
Course assistant: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2011

### RESEARCH VISITS Rennes 4 month research visit

Location: Rennes, France

Institution: Institut national des sciences appliquées de Rennes

Host: Maxime Pelcat, ITER Laboratory

Duration: November 2013 - March 2014

### JOINT-COOPERATION

#### **Green Energy Cloud Simulation**

Partners: Enida Sheme, Polytechnic University of Tirana, Tirana, Albania

Dražen Lučanin, TU Vienna, Vienna, Austria

Duration: August 15 - November 30 2015

## **Energy Efficient Cloud Simulation**

Partners: Dražen Lučanin, Ilia Pietri, Ivona Brandić, TU Vienna, Vienna, Austria

May 15 - May 30 2015 Duration:

#### Power-Aware HEVC Decoding with Tunable Image Quality

Partners: Erwan Nogues, Maxime Pelcat, INSA de Rennes, France

Winter 2014 Duration:

Barrelfish port for Tilera Tile64

Partners: Xiaowen Wang, Robert Radkiewicz, Mats Brorsson, SICS, Stockholm, Sweden

Duration: Summer 2013

Task Migration Mechanism for Distributed Many-Core NoC Systems

Partners: Mohammad Fattah, Amir-Mohammad Rahmani, University of Turku, Finland

Duration: Spring 2013

Safe Motor Controller in Mixed-Critical Environment with Runtime Updating Capabilities

Partners: José Luis Gutiérrez, University of Granada, Spain

Miguel Méndez, Seven Solutions Inc., Spain

Duration: November 5 - November 17 2012

Safe core-to-core channel implementation

Partners: William Davy, Wittenstein Inc., UK

Duration: May 23 - May 24 2012

GRANTS Waldemar von Frenckells stiftelse 2016

For research on energy aware software, 5000€

Oskar Öflunds stiftelse 2016

For research co-operation with FernUniversität in Hagen, Germany, 3000€

Svenska tekniska vetenskapsakademien i Finland 2015

For research visit to FernUniversität in Hagen, Germany, 4500€

Otto Malms stiftelse 2014

For thesis on energy aware software, 5000€

Svenska tekniska vetenskapsakademien i Finland 2013

For research visit to Rennes, France, 2500€

Tekniikan edistämissäätiö 2013

For thesis on energy aware software, 5000€

WORK Åbo Akademi University, Turku, Finland

EXPERIENCE Post-Doc Researcher January 2016 —

Fernuniversität in Hagen, Hagen, Germany

Wissenschaftlicher Mitarbeiter September 2015 –

Åbo Akademi University, Turku, Finland

PhD Student March 2011 – December 2015

Research assistant April 2010 – March 2011

Brisa Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

IT manager May 2009 – September 2009

Herrmans Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

IT support May 2008 – September 2008

Brisa Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

Webshop assistant May 2007 – September 2007

Digicomp Inc., Jakobstad, Finland

Sales person July 2006 – September 2006

Technical support May 2005 – January 2005

 $_{
m REFEREES}$  Prof. Johan Lilius Doc. Sébastien Lafond Prof. Jörg Keller

Professor Assistant Professor Professor Åbo Akademi University Åbo Akademi University Fernuniversität in Hagen

Turku Finland Turku Finland Hagen Germany

phone: available on request phone: available on request phone: available on request

e-mail: johan.lilius@abo.fi e-mail: sebastien.lafond@abo.fi e-mail: joerg.keller@fernuni-hagen.de